Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Associate, Computational Biology Waisman Center, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, 53705, USA Webpage: cngupta.github.io

Email: chiraggupta.bioinfo@gmail.com

Phone: (479) 799-7136

SUMMARY

Bioinformatics Scientist with 8+ years of experience in data-driven scientific investigations of human and plant systems. My objective is to develop bioinformatics solutions for integrating multi-omics data and applications of advanced machine learning techniques to guide clinical decision making and design efficacious wet lab experiments. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 10+ peer reviewed publications, 4+ oral and 10+ poster presentations.

EDUCATION

2017	Ph.D. Cell and Molecular Biology (Computational) Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for systems-level analysis of gene function in plants	University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2009 2007	M.Sc. Bioinformatics B.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India Sardar Patel University, India
_	_	

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

I LOLANCII LAI	LIVILINGE	
2021 – present	 Postdoctoral Research Associate Neuropsychiatric disorders 	University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA
2017 – 2020	 Single cell gene regulatory networks Heterogenous data integration Postdoctoral Research Associate 	University of Arkansas,
	 Rice environmental stress biology Network-based machine learning for gene prioritization Web applications (GRAiN) 	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2012 – 2017	Graduate Research Assistant	University of Arkansas,
	Plant stress and developmental biologyTranscriptomics	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
	Gene coexpression networksWeb applications (RECoN, SANe)	
2008 — 2009	Student Researcher	Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd.,
	Fusion proteins in cancerProtein structure prediction	Gujarat, India
	r	

Molecular modeling, drug designing

PUBLICATIONS

Under review/preprints

1. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. bioRxiv, doi: 10.1101/165894 (in revision)

In preparation

- 1. Applications of artificial intelligence and machine learning to multimodal data in intellectual and developmental disabilities (*review*; 2022)
- 2. Network analysis of primary and secondary cell types of the human brain. (in preparation)

Peer reviewed journal articles

- 1. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. (accepted, Front. in genetics, 2021)
- 2. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2020.00232*.
- 3. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019. doi:10.1104/pp.19.00487*.
- Chirag Gupta and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. F1000Research, Feb. 2019. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.17207.1.
- 5. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2017.01640
- 6. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017. doi:* 10.1038/s41598-017-09542-1.
- 7. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, **Chirag Gupta**, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. *Plant Signaling and Behavior*, *January 2015. doi: 10.1080/15592324.2015.1034421*.

Published project reports

1. Anuj Kumar, Sara Yingling, Julie Thomas, Charles Ruiz, Yheni Dwiningsih, **Chirag Gupta**, Paul Counce, T.J. Siebenmorgen, Karen A.K. Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Screening of Indica and Japonica rice subspecies for grain yield and quality under high nighttime temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2018, 659:61-66.

2. Ramegowda Venkategowda, Subodh Srivastava, Julie Thomas, **Chirag Gupta**, Supratim Basu, Paul Counce, Ya-Jane Wang, Terry Siebenmorgen, Karen Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Genetic basis of altered grain quality in different rice cultivars under high nighttime temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2015, 634:79-85.

Conference Presentations

Talks

- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3rd May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. American Society of Plant Biologists – Southern Section (ASPB-SS), Lexington, KY, 30th March 2014.

Select posters

- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. AR-BIC, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- Differential Co-expression: A new paradigm for identification of candidate genes from expression data. AR-BIC, Little Rock, AR, 24th April 2017
- An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- StarchNet: Implications of high night-time temperature on starch metabolism regulatory networks in rice. AR NSF EPSCoR Annual Meeting, Fayetteville, AR, 15th September 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

AWARDS

- Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, Crops InSilico, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS

- NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018
- **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS

2019 - present The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)

SELECT SKILLS

Programming R, Perl, PHP, mySQL

Bioinformatics Docker, STAR, Tuxedo suite, BWA, Samtools, GATK, Picard, VarScan,

Mutect, SomaticSniper, VCFtools, edgeR, DESeq, limma, LibSVM, Weka,

BLAST, Arguslab, MolSoft, Rasmol, I-TASSER etc.

Visualization R, CytoscapeWeb, D3.js

Platforms UNIX, Linux, Google cloud, MacOS

Version control Github

TOOLS DEVELOPED

GRAINS http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/GRAiN/
SANe https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/
https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

EXTENSION ACTIVITIES

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

ACADEMIC SERVICE

- Manuscript reviewer for Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods
- Plante Fellow 2019: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research
- Member of the panel of judges for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

REFREES

Available upon request